<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ashley Van Spankeren</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 21:25:47 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 21:25:47 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>WTF is MVVM</title>
        <description>&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;POV: It’s the first day of your internship at a tech company. You’re a little nervous, but you know how to reverse a linked list, so you figure you’ve got this. You don’t know exactly what a casual dress code allows, so you opt for something that your grandma would approve of for Sunday dinner; respectable but not trying too hard. Flash forward to your first team meeting: walking through the project code base. Amidst a plethora of abbreviations getting thrown around, the tech lead mentions “… and we use &lt;em&gt;sequel server&lt;/em&gt; for our DBMS”. Wait - that’s how SQL is pronounced? Now you’re panicking, remembering that not only did you call it “ess cue ell” in the interview but you don’t remember the difference between an inner join and outer join.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parsing the jargon used in the world of software development often feels like learning a whole new language (and this is on top of actually learning new programming languages). Here are some terms I wish I knew before starting my first internship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cli-command-line-interface&quot;&gt;CLI (Command Line Interface)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A way to interact with a program using text-based commands (often done through Command Prompt/ Terminal/ your shell of choice). A CLI is a lightweight alternative to a GUI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;gui-graphical-user-interface&quot;&gt;GUI (Graphical User Interface)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often pronounced “gooey”. This is a way to interact with a program through clicking, scrolling, dragging, and dropping. A GUI is a prettier alternative to a CLI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;vcs-version-control-system&quot;&gt;VCS (Version Control System)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a way for teams to keep track of changes to a codebase. If you’re not yet familiar, checkout &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; (pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;front-end&quot;&gt;Front end&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(AKA client side)&lt;br /&gt;
The part of an application that users interact with. Front end code usually looks like HTML, CSS, and Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;back-end&quot;&gt;Back end&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(AKA server side)&lt;br /&gt;
The part of an application that communicates between the database and the browser. Also the part that users don’t see. Back end code may include Java, Python, or C#.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;architecture&quot;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A frustratingly broad term that refers to the structure or design of the codebase. The architecture defines the different elements or layers of the application, as well as properties or relations that exist between them. MVC (model-view-controller) and MVVM (model-view-viewmodel) are two common architectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;saas-software-as-a-service&quot;&gt;SaaS (Software as a Service)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different from &lt;a href=&quot;https://sass-lang.com/&quot;&gt;Sass&lt;/a&gt;, although pronounced the same. SaaS is used interchangeably with “cloud-based solution” and is spoken of fondly because it allows users to access their application from a web browser, rather than downloading and installing it on their computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ide-integrated-development-environment&quot;&gt;IDE (Integrated Development Environment)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application containing tools to assist with software development. Such tools may include a text editor, debugger, and console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;local&quot;&gt;Local&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a program locally means to run it on your current device, rather than on a remote server (or “in production/ beta/ some other environment”). The beauty of running locally is that your changes affect only your local device, i.e. you’re not going to crash that super important client project. When running locally, you can usually access the application and see your changes by going to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;127.0.0.1&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; in a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This just scratches the surface of the ever-expanding terminology used in the software world. The reality is, regardless of how prepared you try to be, the first day (and week and probably month) is going to be like drinking from a fire hose. Stay curious, enjoy the learning process, and ask for clarification. You might not know (yet!) the difference between MySQL and PostgreSQL but hey, at least now you know how to pronounce it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/wtf-is-mvvm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/wtf-is-mvvm</guid>
        
        <category>Co-op</category>
        
        <category>Internship</category>
        
        <category>Tips</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Inconvenient Truths</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Coding is not hard. There. I said it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My sister started coding when she was 8 years old. Maybe she’s a prodigy, but more likely is the elephant in the room that we, as developers, love to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abundance of resources freely and easily accessible is astounding. Regardless of how niche or convoluted the problem may be, there always seems to be a library, or StackOverflow answer to help. I mean, there are packages to find the circumference of the inner ear bone of salmon for goodness sake. So why do we encounter bugs that ? Why do the bulk of software development job descriptions contain a long list of programming languages&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/inconvenient-truths</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/inconvenient-truths</guid>
        
        <category>Startup</category>
        
        <category>Tips</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Choosing the Best Front-end Framework</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In computer science, a &lt;strong&gt;software framework&lt;/strong&gt; is an abstraction in which software providing generic functionality can be selectively changed by additional user-written code, thus providing application-specific software. A software framework provides a standard way to build and deploy applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Walking on water and developing software from a specification are easy if both are frozen.” &lt;cite&gt;- Edward V Berard -&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A software framework is a universal, reusable software environment that provides particular functionality as part of a larger software platform to facilitate development of software applications, products and solutions. Software frameworks may include support programs, compilers, code libraries, tool sets, and application programming interfaces (APIs) that bring together all the different components to enable development of a project or system. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_framework&quot;&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;react&quot;&gt;React&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In computing, &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactjs.org/&quot;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; (sometimes styled React.js or ReactJS) is a JavaScript library for building user interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is maintained by Facebook, Instagram and a community of individual developers and corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;React allows developers to create large web-applications that use data and can change over time without reloading the page. It aims primarily to provide speed, simplicity, and scalability. React processes only user interfaces in applications. This corresponds to View in the Model-View-Controller (MVC) pattern, and can be used in combination with other JavaScript libraries or frameworks in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller&quot;&gt;MVC&lt;/a&gt;, such as AngularJS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vue&quot;&gt;Vue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vuejs.org/&quot;&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;(commonly referred to as Vue; pronounced /vjuː/, like view)&lt;/em&gt; is an open-source progressive JavaScript framework for building user interfaces. Integration into projects that use other JavaScript libraries is made easy with Vue because it is designed to be incrementally adoptable. Vue can also function as a web application framework capable of powering advanced single-page applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ember&quot;&gt;Ember&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://emberjs.com/&quot;&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source JavaScript web framework, based on the Model–view–viewmodel (MVVM) pattern. It allows developers to create scalable single-page web applications by incorporating common idioms and best practices into the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ember is used on many popular websites, including Discourse, Groupon, LinkedIn, Vine, Live Nation, Nordstrom, Twitch.tv and Chipotle. Although primarily considered a framework for the web, it is also possible to build desktop and mobile applications in Ember. The most notable example of an Ember desktop application is Apple Music, a feature of the iTunes desktop application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;angular&quot;&gt;Angular&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AngularJS &lt;em&gt;(commonly referred to as “Angular.js” or “AngularJS 1.X”)&lt;/em&gt; is a JavaScript-based open-source front-end web application framework mainly maintained by Google and by a community of individuals and corporations to address many of the challenges encountered in developing single-page applications. The JavaScript components complement Apache Cordova, the framework used for developing cross-platform mobile apps. It aims to simplify both the development and the testing of such applications by providing a framework for client-side model–view–controller (MVC) and model–view–viewmodel (MVVM) architectures, along with components commonly used in rich Internet applications. In 2014, the original AngularJS team began working on Angular (Application Platform).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AngularJS framework works by first reading the HTML page, which has additional custom tag attributes embedded into it. Angular interprets those attributes as directives to bind input or output parts of the page to a model that is represented by standard JavaScript variables. The values of those JavaScript variables can be manually set within the code, or retrieved from static or dynamic JSON resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to JavaScript analytics service Libscore, AngularJS is used on the websites of Wolfram Alpha, NBC, Walgreens, Intel, Sprint, ABC News, and about 12,000 other sites out of 1 million tested in October 2016. AngularJS is currently in the top 100 of the most starred projects on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AngularJS is the frontend part of the &lt;strong&gt;MEAN stack&lt;/strong&gt;, consisting of MongoDB database, &lt;a href=&quot;https://expressjs.com/&quot;&gt;Express.js&lt;/a&gt; web application server framework, Angular.js itself, and Node.js server runtime environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/choosing-the-best-front-end-framework</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/choosing-the-best-front-end-framework</guid>
        
        <category>JavaScript</category>
        
        <category>Tips</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
